Hey there everyone, my name is and I
make coding videos. In this video I
would love to walk you through that
there are certain platforms which are
challenging the traditional route of
building the applications and especially
on the back end side. You have already
seen a lot of backends in Java,
JavaScript, Express,
NexJS and a whole bunch of things. But
there are few new players in the market
which are challenging this traditional
way of developing the back end. and I'm
super excited, super interesting in
them. One such player is Moshia which
was also trending a few days ago on the
GitHub and I recently created a video
about exploring their platform and their
philosophy of building. In this video
together for the very first time I want
to build an application with them, what
it's like to build or initiate an
application, what kind of a code files
they generate and how does it look like
to have the very basic app. I did one
such video for the nextjs as well when
the nextjs came out and I was super
happy that I was learning along with
you. I want to repeat this again. Maybe
this is going to be the next another
nextjs or uh but for the back end but I
would love to explore with that. So with
that let me take you onto the screen and
together let's explore this versel but
for back end known as motia. And here is
the first website. And yes, of course,
just like NexJS, they also give you this
nice button at the very front. But what
I want to do is I want to go in the docs
and I want to see what it's like. So
they have this getting started. Welcome
to Moshia. All right, that's good.
That's good. We have already explored
this part most of it and yeah, this is
my favorite part that I can just build
application in whatever the language I
want. But where I am interested in this
particular video is quick start. So what
it's like to create uh the very first
application. By the way, you can copy
the markdown and open this up into a lot
of things. Even T3 chat I give you for
that. Didn't even thought of that. So
yeah, they're very generous in that. But
what I want is I would love to copy
this. I already have this VS Code setup
in the Chai theme. and let's go ahead
and see what it's like to have this one.
All right, fingers all crossed and let's
see. Okay, so Moshia, yes, I would like
to proceed. Couple of questions.
Hopefully, it will ask. No questions.
Ask some questions.
It doesn't do anything. All right, I'll
wait for it. And I really like these
kinds of raw videos where we together
explore what's happening, what's not
happening, how much time it's taking.
All right. So,
all right. So, a couple of questions.
What template would you like to use? You
can use your base as Python and base as
TypeScript. I'm I'll prefer to go with
the TypeScript. Maybe another video for
Python, but this time we'll choose this
one. And it says uh project name leave
blank to use current folder. I'll not
give them I'll just call this one as my
motia app. I think that would be good.
But if I just leave this I think this
will populate my current folder. That
would be better instead of creating a
folder inside a folder. So I'll just
leave this as a blank. I think that
would be better. Proceed. Yes, of
course. Please do that. All right. So we
have a lot of configuration folder and
even a cursor folder is being created. I
like that they are going really forward.
Uh yes please access whatever you need.
All right so it says dependency
installed flow default created steps. I
would love to explore what do you all
create and how it is going on. So let's
go ahead and have a deep dive. All
right. So cursor of course you have a
lot of cursor API docs and stuff
instruction good stuff. Node modules, no
need to go inside that. First, let's see
what's package.json. How does it look
like? Name, current folder. Okay.
Description, nothing. Script. We have
post install script, which is motion
install. We have dev, dev, debug,
generate types, build, clean. Good
stuff. And uh really interesting to see
mermaid as well here. Then we have
keyword dependency. Not much. Moshia and
by default they go with the zod. So they
do care about the type safety as well.
Of course, it's TypeScript. So,
TypeScript node, nothing too drastic.
And it comes up with a default types of
React, but not React. Interesting stuff.
And we have TypeScript node. That's
okay. Now, let's see what's there in the
TS config standard.
Uh types we do have. I don't think so we
need to worry too much about this. This
is okay part. And this is what happens
when the first time you see the
application. This is the learning
journey. And I'm totally believing that
you will also appreciate this. A lot of
time tutorials are just hey just walk me
through I'll give you the explanation.
This is for the first time we both are
learning together. I think this is the
best part of it. Then we have this
motion workbench.
Okay. So there are steps which is
noopstepts some x and y coordinate
source handle position. Right. So I
think they are plotting something. This
is exactly for that. We will see that
when we'll run the application because a
lot of things gets clear when you run
the application. And as they say that
whole of their journey is on the steps
in case you don't know that uh let me
take you back onto this. If you read a
little bit in their manifesto they
actually mention this uh front here that
we declare the step is our core
primitive. So they actually ship the
core primitive as steps. Okay. So these
are the steps uh 0000 steps tsx. Then we
have the step ts. I think this is for
exactly the react and this is the one.
So we don't have much of them. We have
the step one as API step. Then we have
test state step and the check state
step. Okay let's explore each one of
this file. Noop step don't hold any
logic in the code. They are a way to
create custom nodes for flows on the
workbench and represent external states
such as human in the loop. H nice. I
would love to run this to see that what
happens. Let's see. We forgot to check
the docs. So, we need to check the docs
again. And quick start. This is what
I've done. And now it says npx motion
dev. All right. Let's go ahead and uh
use this npxia dev. So, this is what the
documentation mentioned. I don't need to
go in the folder. I was little smart
there.
Okay. And this is how we're going to see
something. All right. Fair enough. Fair
enough. Let's go up here. npx run motion
dev. All the flows are being created and
we should be technically listening on
this port. It's been long that I have
seen this port. Usually it's local host.
Okay.
Ooh, that's interesting one here. So we
have the tracing. Ah, you need to see
this. So there we go. So we have this
whole thing. And by the way, some other
stuff is running up. I'll close that. So
we have tracing logs and the states
and we have these endpoints being
defined. We just have the default
template as of now and warning light
mode coming up. There we go. I'll not
keep it. So if I start this flow
uh let's click on the start flow. I
think this is the API trigger which
actually triggers this and this sets any
changes up here. So I can see the whole
flow of how the endpoints and how the
steps are being created. Can I minimize
this? Yeah, that's that's a lot.
All right. I can change this change this
and
that's nice.
Oh, nice zoom and stuff is also there.
So probably I should be able to change
them. All right, looks good. I need to
read more on the docs that what's
happening. Key test welcome to Moshia
state change. Oh, so the every time I
was clicking on it, it was actually
looking on this one. H So let me go
ahead. It it was logging all the time
and stuff. If I click this again, yep,
it's actually matches the state value.
Key is test. Welcome to Moshia.
Good stuff. Let's go ahead and explore
how the documentation and steps looks
like. I think the good point just a gut
feeling is 01 step. All right. So it
says API route config and the handlers
these are imported from the motion
itself and then we have API route config
which where we have to config uh the
type is API and the name is trigger.
What more type do you have?
It is just the type API as of now. At
least the suggestions are saying one.
The good thing is Typescript so I can
rely a lot on the suggestion and just
like you can see in here if I just
remove this and hit this notice here all
the suggestions are there. So I'm
relying on that. So the name is API
trigger. The description is default
template API trigger. I think this is
the one that is there.
Let's see. And then we have the API
step. This emits a test state. Can I
emit something else? I would check that.
Then the body is schema which says the
message
string expected request body for type
checking. Good stuff. Let me check this.
And this is how you learn. Then we have
a handler which takes couple of
parameter. The first one is request. And
then we have logger emit and trace ID.
And then we can use the logger to trace
this step zero processing API and the
body request. Did we saw something like
that?
Did we saw? So, yep, we have state
change, the API trigger, step one,
processing API. So, I think this is
exactly coming up from here. And then we
have the step. We don't have anything
inside the body. This is exactly where
it's coming up. And we also emit an
event so that I guess another event can
pick it up. So, emit events to the topic
to process asynchronously. That's nice.
So, topic is the test state and the data
that you probably can pass on and then
return back to the client. So whoever
the client is requesting we can actually
return them and let it go. And this is
the part which probably goes to the next
step. Event emit events to the topics to
process a synchronously.
Good. Let's go into the test state.
This is the second one. All right. So
this is a type event. This is event
config. What was the previous one? The
previous one was the API route config.
And this is the event config. How many
options we have here?
Just one. So event config you have to
mention it always as event. Then we have
the name description. This step
subscribes to the event test state to be
processed as synchronously. So we have
to subscribe to a test state. All right.
So we are subscribing to an event test
state which is coming up from the
previous step or any step maybe because
you are subscribed. So it doesn't need
to come from the previous one. It can
come from anyone. As long as this event
is emitted, I'll start working. And this
one also emits a check state change. So,
anybody can actually subscribe just by
writing this. But this needs to go into
the event config uh configuration.
Fairly understandable. And this is in
reality how you understand a fresh new
technology. I have never made this kind
of videos, but this is how the struggle
goes up. You go into the docs, you
create the fresh project, you put up
your theories, test them out, you fail
with them, you work with them and this
is how it works. This is obvious and
this is the portion where your existing
knowledge overlaps. So I have worked
quite a lot with the zod. So those
knowledge from react or nextjs this
overlaps. So this makes life a little
easier. But this is the first time that
we are seeing all of this. So we have
the flows now default. Do we have more
of the flows? The flow this step belongs
to V will be available in the workbench.
Okay. And this is the handler. I guess
handlers are handlers. This is where you
write your business logic. Avoid using
console log. Use logger instead. So they
have their own logger. And this is where
you mention and I think we also hit
this. So this is the step two where we
change the step pushing message content
to the state. Right now we have don't
have anything in the input but we could
have something here. All right. So
persist content on the state and then we
are also emitting the event which is
check state change and the data we are
seeing key as test expected message. All
right, fair enough. Let's go into the
next one. And then we also see this here
again the same event. We are checking
the state change. Anything you can
change. You subscribe for an event. You
can also emit emit any event. You
validate your input and then you can
mark this into a flow so that it's
available in this workbench.
All right. in the default because there
could be other. I just noticed there
could be many workbenches up here. Good
enough. And then we simply see the
handler which check the uh check for the
state change and then you write the
logic here
and there we have the values. We fetch
the values if the value is not as
expected.
I guess this is the straightforward
business logic. So what I've understood
as a conclusion as of now there are
couple of key interesting points and
then I jump into the docs to validate my
theory. So there are two major thing the
first one is somebody is hitting the
endpoint. So there is API route config
and after that once we have hit the API
endpoint what do we want to do comes
under the event config or event
configuration. You can actually
subscribe to any event and also as well
as you can emit any event. So rest of
things is abstracted from us. They say
rightly about the framework. This is a
framework. So we can subscribe to any
event and can emit any event and any of
the step can actually subscribe and
event emit the events there and then all
of them also gets a handler that what
you really want to do. So you simply do
export con handler and handlers then
handle this part here. So set change
this is what we are taking and this is
where we write the business logic. All
right fair enough. Let's also dive deep
into this one that how this is this is
basically just the react nodes. So what
you see here this is known as the nodes.
So I think these are being created. This
is a standard react stuff. Uh don't need
to dive much into this and this is where
I configure my application to call this
one as /defaults. The flows is going to
be default. Uh good enough. Fair enough
stuff in here. All right, let's check
couple of more things. Now this one
makes sense that we have the steps where
on X and Y location they will be there
target all of that. So how they are
working on this configuration file is
making sense. Now let's jump into the
docs part how that is there. All right.
So this is the project structure. We can
go ahead and check this.
And this is the project structure. say
so they say the basic project structure
will be like your project then you have
the steps it could be API gateway and
then the processor self notification
anything like that and we have the
custom UI steps as well fairly fairly
simple project structure I was expecting
much more file than this but turns out
it's actually not that hard and we have
automatic step discovery I like that I
don't have to do this stuff discovery
rules I really really need to go and
dive deep into This also they have the
naming con file naming convention as
well. I need to study that so that I can
give you a gist of it, summary of it. Uh
I love doing that things because I go
dive into the documentation take
everything that they have to offer and
then bring out a short guide for you to
actually understand and get into this.
So I think hope you understood the
process of how we do the things and yes
each of the new framework that I dive in
this is what it takes. I create the
project then dive into it explore the
files put up my theories match this
theory with the docs and now what I'll
do is for the next 2 hours 3 hours
whatever it takes I'll be diving into
their docs yeah line by line and we'll
extract the information we'll make my
notes and then probably in the next
video I'll come back and we'll explain
to you and we'll build together a sample
project it will be basic but it will
actually
kind of validate our theories whatever
we have made so far because these
frameworks are knew nobody is an expert
here except the creators. So we need to
put out our theory join their discord
and go and work with them that how it is
going like so technically you are for
the first time seeing what it takes
behind the scene to explore a framework
and learn with that. I hope you're
enjoying these raw format because I
think nobody does that on the YouTube
itself. And for this I highly highly
would appreciate if you will drop some
comment that hey we love this behind the
scene and in the next video together we
are going to explore a simple to-do kind
of application with this that what
possibly can be a really bare minimum
application with Moshia. That is it for
this video. Let's catch up in the next
one.